[Music]
This is software engineering radio the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net SE radio is.
brought to you by the ITE computer society.
and by it e software magazine online at computer.org/software.
[Music]
Hello everyone welcome to this episode of software and sharing radio.
Our guest today is John Lee.
Chan Lee is a co-founder and chief architect at Deboss.
Before founding DeBoss, Chan completed her PhD in computer science at Stanford in 2023.
Her PhD research has focused on abstractions for efficient and reliable cloud computing.
Chan is also the co-organizer of the South Systems Club,
which is an independent talk series focusing on systems programming.
Before we actually talk a little bit more about deboss and its research origins.
I'd like to point listeners to episode 596 which is Maxim Fatib on durable execution with temporal.
There are also a few other episodes we have done on related topics.
and I'll put those in the show notes.
These are episode 351, 223 and 198.
So happy to have you here Chon to talk about deboss and durable execution.
Welcome to the show.
Would you like to add something to your bio before we jump right in?
Thanks for inviting me to the show.
Yeah, so originally DeBoss started as a joint research project.
It's a collaboration between Stanford and MIT.
So we started the project since 2020.
It was also led by the Postgress creator professor Mike Stonereaker.
and the spark creator and database co-founder Matezah.
So during the research project, we really tested the capability of databases.
and see how databases can help you create reliable programs.
and how databases can help you make your programs more observable and debugable.
So during the research project, we built several prototypes.
and we wrote several papers and when we presented it,
people are really excited about the capability that deboss can bring.
So when we graduated in 2023, we decided to based on the research project co-ound deboss.
and deboss as a company right now we focus on building durable software.
and we believe that all software should be reliable and observable and scalable by default.
So now deboss stands for durable backends observable and scalable.
So you mentioned the use of databases for basically running your applications.
but why is that a new concept?
Everybody uses databases for running apps or most people do.
So what is the difference here? What is the secret sauce that you talking about?
Yeah.
So it's true that people have been storing their business critical data in databases for like 30 40. years.
but the new concept is that we also want to persist programs execution state in the database.
like here's your program and it has multiple steps and we want to persist the steps output.
and the input into the database so.
that if your program crashes or machine failed we'll be able to resume from exactly.
where you left off.
So the idea is to in addition to your application data,
we also store your program execution state in the database.
Especially if you're having long running and dynamic workflows in your programs,
you really don't want to restart from scratch every time you hit a system error.
or you have a machine failure.
So Chan, maybe you can explain to the listeners what exactly do you define a workflow as opposed.
to a service? Yeah.
So to get started I think we can talk about what is a workflow in this context.
So traditionally people think workflows as state machines.
You have to define a DAC stuff like that.
But actually in deboss anything can be a workflow.
So to give a concrete example a workflow is a sequence of operations or function calls.
So a very typical example in like durable execution is let's say checkout service.
So if you're implementing a checkout service usually you have to call say reserve inventory you have to.
update a database to make sure that you have enough inventory.
and then after that if you successfully reserve the inventory you will cut out to the payment process.
for example this could be an external service like stripe.
or PayPal you will say I want to charge a user this much.
and after that you need to wait for the response from those services.
and then based on the result you will decide whether to fulfill the order.
and send a confirmation email to the user.
or you have to undo your reservation for the inventory.
and then cancel the order and send a cancellation email.
So this process can be abstracted as a workflow.
and then like what guarantees do we want for this workflow?
First we want to make sure that once I click.
that check out button all steps will eventually succeed or complete.
Right?
I don't want to say I pay for my process.
but I never receive my item or I reserve the inventory but never charge the user.
So that's the first guarantee and the second guarantee is that I want to guarantee effectively exactly once.
So if I charge a user I want to charge them once.
and if I reserve the inventory I also want to only reserve it once.
So you talked about workflow and you mentioned transaction.
What's the relationship?
So in this context a transaction is essentially interaction to a local database.
and then a workflow can be composed of transactions.
and also external services or we just call it steps in general.
So in deboss a workflow is a sequence of steps.
and some steps could be transactions that talk to a database.
and other normal steps well normal steps can be any functions right can be talking to external APIs.
or can have some any non-deterministic factors operations in.
that step but overall the workflow needs to be deterministic.
and determinism and item potency are two foundations for durable workflows.
and essentially What we build is a library that you can just easily install it.
and then add annotations to your program.
So I described the checkout workflow to make it durable in deboss.
You essentially put annotation at deboss.workflow in front of the overall orchestration workflow function.
and then you put at step at the function definition of every individual step.
Then when we call that function essentially we'll first we.
basically put wrappers around those functions to make them durable.
So to make it more concrete basically.
when you start a workflow when you start call the workflow function the wrapper would first checkpoint the.
input of the workflow. in the database.
and then for each step we first check have we executed this step before.
If so, we directly read the recorded output from the database.
and return the output instead of re-executing it.
So this way we guarantee exactly once.
So the thing is for external systems the way to guarantee exactly once is to guarantee at least. once plus item potency key.
and deboss basically automatically generates an item potency key per workflow and per step.
So we can guarantee that each step will execute effectively exactly once.
and then after each step finishes we'll checkpoint the output into the database.
and so on so forth until we reach the end of the workflow.
and say if something crashes in the middle.
when we recover the deboss library will look into the database and see which workflow is still pending.
And then if the workflow is still pending,
we'll just essentially replay the workflow from the start and walk through all the steps.
And then for the finished steps, we'll already see the database record.
And then we'll skip those steps.
And then we'll eventually lend to the last completed step.
and then we'll continue resume the workflow from where it left off.
So that's basically a highle idea of how deboss.
You mentioned the item potency key.
explain that further.
Yeah.
So essentially item potency key is a way to guarantee.
that each step is executed once and only once.
So essentially when you work with external API say stripe payment.
right you want to say I only want to charge it this user once.
and then you can pick it back a item potency key in your request to stripe.
So if Stripe received the same key again,
it will not issue another invoice to the user,
Stripe will be able to look up its own database.
and say, "Hey, I already have an outstanding invoice for this checkout session.".
So they will only charge a user once.
So I think item potency is a very important concept in terms of durable execution.
And in Deboss, we automatically generate an item potency key for a workflow.
if you don't already provide one.
And then for each step we'll basically append the step sequence number to it.
So every step in the workflow will also be uniquely identified.
So the reason we need item potency key is.
that you can't really control external systems right say even if we only call stripe API once.
We don't know whether the network connection will fail.
or maybe stripe will fail or there's some intermediate transient errors that may happen.
So like if we don't get the result back, we may think it failed.
but in order to make sure that the checkout goes through,
we may want to retry it and we retry it.
We can't generate a new session because maybe the stripe payment already succeeded,
but it just the network was cut when Stripe tried to send the result back.
So we have to retry it.
And when we retry it, the way to tell Stripe.
that this is the same checkout request I sent it before is to append the item potency key.
So item policy key is the key to guarantee correctness.
and exactly once execution when you work with external systems.
Could you talk more about the deboss architecture?
You did talk about the workflow and the step.
Is there any other key elements of the architecture you'd like people to know about.
and especially if they have origins in the research that you had done in the past?
Yeah.
So deboss workflows and steps and transactions were implemented directly as SQL interactions in the library.
And then beyond that we also have several other primitives.
The one is widely used is called deboss cues.
So we also implement cues on top of postgress.
With cues basically you will be able to group.
So instead of directly invoking or executing a workflow synchronously,
you can incue a workflow and then other workers will be able to pick it up.
So the Q is also just a database record, right?
We just inq by saying here's the task,
here's a Q name and then for the worker they can just pull from each Q.
So the benefit of Q is that it makes it really easy to control concurrency and rate limiting.
Say for example we can have different cues like open AIQ, cloud Q, stuff like that.
and we want to say for the open AIQ we only want to send the request five times. per minute.
So this is a way to group your invocations.
and to control how many outstanding requests you send to external systems.
And another thing is based on research is messaging system.
So when workflows and steps basically they are all within the deboss territory.
but when you need to interact with external systems you need a way to communicate with the workflow.
So give an example of this so say actually the checkout workflow right.
when you call stripe you don't block and wait until user to pay out.
So what you actually do is that Stripe will directly return a confirmation saying.
okay we are processing your payment.
but when your payment is done we'll send you a web hook invocation to say this payment is.
done. and now how to do it in deboss is.
that so in a workflow we can have a deboss receive on a specific topic waiting for the. specific stripe payment.
session.
and then we can implement a web hook.
that listens Stripe call back when a stripe call back we can extract.
because as we mentioned we have the item policy key we can uniquely identify.
which workflow we should call back to.
and then we will be able to send say deboss send with.
that item potency key and then send stripe payments result either paid or payment rejected stuff like that.
and then the workflow well using the receive will be able to get.
that information so this is really useful if you want to like I think almost all.
the payment system for example is using this type of pattern.
and also if you want anything that goes to like human in the loop say you want to. send a human verification email.
and then you want to wait for the human confirmation to come back you can't just block there.
and wait you have to wait for a call back.
and then deboss send and receive primitive allows you to do that.
and this library is what you call as deboss transact.
Anybody can use it as long as they annotate their code. Yes.
So deboss transact is an open source library. It's MIT license.
So anyone will be able to use it.
It's currently available in Typescript and Python.
So we are adding more language support.
So for the audience if you have any feedback on what languages you wish to see,
please contact us and we'll add more.
So for the transact library you can install it and run it anywhere.
What is the deboss cloud?
Right.
So deboss cloud is a serverless hosting platform for transact applications.
So say so you can run your transact applications anywhere on your own laptop. or on a kubernetes cluster.
But if you don't have any resources.
and if you don't want to manage any clusters you can deploy your app to deboss cloud.
So if I do use deboss transact library I must get a Postgress can I.
if I wanted to use another database system could I currently deboss transact supports.
any Postgress compatible databases so you can use it with your own Postgress server like many of our.
users just simply add deboss transact.
because they already have a Postgress server.
so they just use the same server to store your execution state data.
but you can also use other offerings like each cloud provider has some Postgress offering.
and we also compatible with new serverless Postgress like neon.
or superbase or cockroach db or yugabet db there are a lot of options here.
so is that just because that's the database you tested with.
or is there any specific features of postgress postcress compatible databases.
that you leverage yeah I guess it goes.
back to the question of why do we choose postgress.
So like there are a couple of reasons we chose Postgress.
First is that the ecosystem is huge.
As I said there are a lot of providers in the cloud.
or there are a lot of on-prem solutions as well.
People know how to operate Postgress.
It's a very mature and battle tested technology and people really trust Postgress. So that's one reason.
And the second reason is that it's a relational database.
So it has built-in transactions. It's very reliable.
So we don't need to worry about like it has backups.
and it has replication if you want to.
And finally the extension ecosystem is great.
Some of our users actually use Postgress as a vector store.
So some people also use Postgress to store time series data.
So really like with a single database you can achieve a lot of things.
You can store basically all data from transactional data to analytics data to vector data.
So we really like this versality of Postgress.
So Chen, a lot of our listeners I think are really interested in the how like peering behind.
the black box.
So if they will have access to the Postgress database.
where the state is getting stored if they peak in there what will they see.
and where should they peak? Yeah.
So Debb stores all the information in the separate logical database inside the Postgress server.
So you can think of a logical database is another namespace within the Postgress server to isolate it.
from your main application database so that we don't interrupt.
or we don't disturb your normal tables or your normal queries.
So in that database under the deboss schema you will be able to find several tables.
that stores information.
So there are several tables you want to look into.
The first is workflow status table.
That's the core table that stores workflow information.
And then when you first execute a workflow, it will say workflow pending.
And then as your workflow progress and eventually succeed or fail,
we'll update the workflow status to error with the error the actual error.
or success with the actual output.
So that table is the core that drives the deboss that stores the state changes of deboss.
And then the second table you want to look at is operation outputs table.
In that table, that's where we store the serialized output of each step.
And by looking into that table, you will see the workflow ID.
and then the step ID inside the workflow and the result of every single step.
So by looking at those two tables,
you can piece together what workflow has executed when and what steps has executed at what time stamp.
Besides that, we also have the workflow cues table.
The Q's table basically groups workflows into different cues.
And then by saying different Q's, it's just we assign a different name in the Q names table.
And that will allow us to quickly look up what workflows are assigned to be executed in. that queue.
So I would say the real beauty is in SQL.
You can use SQL to manage your workflows.
and you can also use SQL to simply query them and observe what happened in your system.
Do you provide out of the box visualizations for what you see in these tables?
Yes.
So if you log into deboss console like console.debos.dev you'll be able to see we have table visualization.
you can basically select.
or filter based on the workflow names or based on workflow status.
And we are also actively developing a graph visualization of the workflow execution graph.
So say what workflow has started and how many steps it has finished.
and like what's a workflow parent child relationship between different workflows.
Say like one workflow can invoke subworkflow that execute other tasks.
So you'll be able to connect the dots by looking at that graph.
Chan, do you have any real world example.
where maybe talking to your customers where unreliable workflow executions cause them really problematic system failures or inefficiencies?
Yeah.
So let's see there are several use cases.
My favorite one is that one of our customers have to persist data across multiple systems.
Say Shopify sends some data through Kafka and for each message each message contains some customer data.
They want to persist in their local Postgress database.
They want to persist in their CRM.
They're want to persist in their ERP system.
So they want to make sure that the data is consistent across all systems.
So they chose Deboss.
And if you don't have correct customer data, you can probably lose customers.
So that's what they really don't want to see.
And deboss guarantees that whenever you receive a message from Kafka,
we guarantee that the message will appear across all systems.
Maybe that answers one of my questions,
which was why would I not roll my own.
or use code generators to help me write the code for durable execution.
I think one of what you say tells me.
that there's a lot of guarantees and compliance that using deboss might help me with. Is that fair?
Are you going through some kind of compliance process that people can leverage?
Yeah.
So I think we can talk a bit more about the observability angle of deboss.
So because everything is stored in Postgress, it's really easy to query and visualize what's going on.
So my favorite quote from customers is that they said deboss is great because everything is in Postgress.
I can just use SQL queries to see what workflows have run,
what workflows failed and what happened at each step.
And based on the information we store in Postgress,
we are also developing more observability features like graph visualization of the workflow.
and its steps and the workflow maybe spawning multiple workflows there.
So we are visualizing the parent child relationship there.
and more than that what we can provide is actually management over your workflows.
So because those are just database records.
if you want to say resume a workflow you can just reincue it put it back into a.
Q table.
If you want to cancel workflow then you can just mark the workflow as canled.
and then the downstream process will just cancel the operation.
And if you want to say, we can talk more about it later.
when we talk about operations with deboss.
but like if you want to restart a workflow with your new versions of a code,
you can just copy the workflow input information.
and assign it with a new item potency key and then just start execution on the new version.
And because data is in Postgress is a relational database is structured data.
and structured data is really easy to analyze and to observe.
A little bit of segue here and would like to contrast deboss with solutions already in the market.
and I did mention our earlier episode the latest one being with Maxim Fativ on temporal.
How does deboss contrast with temporal and is your definition of workflow consistent with temporal's definition of workflow.
and durable execution? Yeah.
So that's a good question and we got asked about that question a lot.
So I think the workflow definition in deboss.
and temporal are essentially the same but the core difference is how we perceive the implementation of this.
durable execution.
So in temporal we call the pattern external orchestration pattern.
With external orchestration which means you have to start a temporal server.
and then when you run your workflow.
instead of directly executing each step your workflow function will need to incue a step into a temporal. worker.
and then temporal worker temporal server will.
instead push the notification or will instead notify a worker node to process that. They call it activity.
We call it a step.
And then after the worker node finishes a step or activity,
they will send it back to temporal server.
and temporal server will persist the result and then send it back to the main workflow function.
So basically for every invocation of your step there are multiple network hops.
and then by contrast in deboss we essentially embed dup execution in your program.
So when you call the workflow it's just a function call.
and when a workflow calls a step it's again it's a function call.
but a function call is intercept by the deboss library.
So everything will happen just in your program.
So we believe the benefit of deboss is that it's really simple.
All you need is your program and your postgress database.
You don't have to deploy an extra orchestration server.
and you don't have to deploy like distributed workers to process your steps.
I get the part about not having to deploy an orchestration server.
but then how do you achieve orchestration?
So deboss implements job execution this as orchestration.
So just to clarify that we achieve job execution by intercepting the function calls.
So you can think of it as.
when you call a deboss decorated function.
instead of directly executing the function we wrap around the workflow function for example to say.
we first persist the input and then call the function.
When execute the workflow function the workflow function will call each step.
and again each step is also wrapped by deboss.
So in the wrapper deboss will first check.
if the step has finished before if not execute it persist the result.
if it has been executed before directly return.
a result so everything happens in the language layer.
so that's why we don't need to send it over to a separate worker to a separate message. cue to achieve.
this is there any other areas where it's important to compare.
and contrast with temporal I think The two main area one is simplicity like in order to add.
deboss to your program it's really simple you install it.
as a library add to your existing program by decorating your functions and you're done.
and then to implement something temporal you have to.
basically restructure program into like you have to think in a distributed system way every time. when you cut out.
a step it is essentially an RPC call to another worker.
and then to executed and and then wait for the result to come back.
So we think simplicity is the number one differentiator and then it's also very simple to operate.
So say like to run deboss in production all you need is a Postgress server.
and then basically people already know how to operate Postgress servers.
So we don't add much of the operational overhead to it.
By contrast, if you use any like external orchestration services,
you have to host their service or you have to rely on their cloud providers cloud offerings.
For example, every time you want to call a step, you have to communicate to their cloud. and say, I want to execute a step.
and their cloud will send a message to worker to execute it. So on so forth.
So that will also give some like implication to performance, right?
In deboss every step is we'll add basically add a database right.
which is like a few milliseconds while if you do everything over the network that will easily go.
a few hundred a millisecond.
Other than the simplicity of use do you have any thoughts about.
when a developer should when they need durable execution they should consider deboss versus temporal?
Yeah I mean temporal is really great technology like it's used by a lot of companies.
I think one benefit of the temporal model is.
that if you want to have a workflow that's consisted of different steps.
or written different languages, it could be easier to use the temporal model.
Say you have a workflow written in Python,
but maybe some steps are written in Go, other in Java and Rust.
If you have such heterogeneous workflow, it will currently be easier to do it in temporal.
Well, on the other hand, if your program is just in Python or TypeScript,
it will definitely be easier to do in Deboss.
In fact, like a current trend is we call full stack applications.
So, when users write their front end code in Typescript,
they actually also want to write their backend in Typescript.
So, that's why like deboss in this case makes more sense because it's very lightweight.
You just add it as another uh TypeScript library and then use it in a program.
How much of this comparison also applies to some of the other technologies like AWS step functions?
Yeah, so the external orchestration part is the same.
So we actually had some performance benchmarks against step functions.
and we found that for deboss we are like each step is like a few milliseconds.
whereas in step functions.
every time you have to schedule a step it will push to a que.
and then you have to dq and wait for result.
So it will come back as like 200 milliseconds.
So the performance gap is pretty large.
And another difference is that step functions requires you to use a late JSON description language like to.
ident to basically specify the DAC.
and that could be another overhead I would say.
Well though like step functions also provide a graphical interface.
You can drag and drop your workflows into a DAC.
This is really nice and this can be used by like for example developers.
or people without too much coding experience.
However, the problem is that it's very easy to use when you have simple tasks.
But when you have a more complicated task, it's hard to manage.
Just share an anecdote from our conversations with users.
someone was switching from step functions to deboss.
because they said eventually they gave up on code review.
because they have to review 3,000 lines of JSON code.
and then in that case using deboss is better.
because all your workflow logic is essentially just your code.
So you write workflows as code and then you can do code review,
you can do your debugging normally as you would when you develop your functions.
A follow-up question there.
In some of the previous episodes on this topic,
there was pros and cons of the graphical representation discussed.
Certainly, there was a sentiment expressed that developers are not very fond of the graphical representation,
but more business users find it useful.
What is your experience there? And if I did want to communicate.
that with a business user and I was as a developer using deboss, what are my options? Yeah, that's a great question.
I think I have the same experience when talking to uh developers.
They usually say they want code.
They want to see code.
But when we talk to more business focused people, they want to see like what's going on.
Like say they want to have a visual.
or a graph visualization of what happened like how many steps happened, how many workflows happened.
and if something failed, which step failed.
So in deboss we basically provide we are.
actually actively developing a graphical visualization based on the information stored in database.
and the reason is that so you can't define workflows based on graph.
but we provide observability into what happened what have executed before I think. that is a good balance I'd say.
because developers usually use code to develop their workflows.
well Business focused people usually need to see what happened like the execution of those workflows. I think that's a good combination.
You had talked earlier about scheduling how one would achieve that.
Can you talk about roll back with deboss?
Because roll back was another big plus of a workflow system or be able to achieve that.
How would I as a developer achieve that if I was using deboss?
Yeah.
So if you use deboss, you can just handle exceptions normally as you would.
when you develop your API or your service.
So in the checkout example, so if I receive if the workflow says sees the payment was failed,
then you will need to call the undo inventory reservation function.
and it also need to call some functions to cancel the order.
So in deboss you basically express them in code as error like.
if you see this error call those sequence of functions.
If you see other types of error do something else.
So we do ask users to explicitly specify the roll back actions.
And the roll back actions are also steps.
So the benefit of using deboss is.
that we'll guarantee everything the workflow that all the steps will run to completion.
How do I as a developer take an existing body of code and the annotations that debus wants? What process would I go through?
Yeah, so we think it's pretty easy.
So you first install the library.
Uh if you use Python, it's pip install.
If you use hyperscript, it's npm install.
And then after that, you can just import deboss.
And then you say you have a function you want to be a workflow.
You just decorate it as at deboss.workflow.
and then within that workflow function you will see what function calls it makes.
and then you decorate those functions as at deboss.step.
I think my question was more like how do I figure out.
which functions I should now go and decorate.
All right.
So I think you essentially decorate any functions.
that will talk to external APIs or talk to the database.
anything that will generate side effects outside of your program.
Thanks, Chan.
So, I'd like to now go into a different section.
where we talk about maybe the more use cases that we see for durable execution,
especially with AI agents.
Before we go there, is there anything else you'd like to add?
Yeah, so actually I like to talk a bit more about workflow recovery.
and failure recovery when you use in production.
So as we talked earlier, it's true that developers can write checkpointing code manually.
but you want to use a job execution system.
or a library like deboss or others because you want to have automatic recovery.
So give you a concrete example in production you usually you have to deploy your code in multiple.
if you use Kubernetes you will deploy to multiple containers or pods.
and in a large production development you could probably develop maybe a 100.
or a thousand pods that each will serve.
well you will load balance between those pods to serve requests.
So the problem is that at any point in time.
or within any hour some pods will definitely fail.
So it's a probability to fail is high when you have a large deployment.
And if you already use Kubernetes, you may think yes, I can just restart those pods.
But the problem is that sure when you restart a pod,
you still need some application logic to decide how to resume the work you've done before before you. crash.
And if you use deboss, we provide a service called conductor.
So this service basically connects to your running applications.
and then it will detect when some of the workers are failing.
So if it detects some workers failed,
it will try to redistribute the pending workflows running on that worker to other healthy workers.
And this way we automatically recover from failures.
and we guarantee that all workflows will eventually run to completion.
So I think this is one reason.
that you really want to delegate this kind kind of recovery to some library or services like deboss.
How does that coexist with the recovery mechanisms in Kubernetes?
Yeah.
So in Kubernetes basically when you restart it will restart your application.
but it doesn't have any application semantics.
It doesn't know what workflows failed before.
Essentially deboss as a library will have some background threads to listen for tasks say you have to.
recover this and that.
So deboss will dispatch certain recovery commands to your workers.
and this works perfectly with other mechanisms in like say kubernetes or other deployments.
So what you mean is that I develop my application with the deboss transact library.
and then when I deploy it to production I can leverage deboss conductor whether.
or not I'm deploying to kubernetes.
Yes, exactly.
Do you use deboss conductor automatically in the deboss cloud?
Yes, we have the same capability in deboss cloud.
So if you deploy to deboss cloud you have all the automatic recovery plus autoscaling.
All right, let's spend some time on AI agents.
That was one big use case on your website.
Why is the problem surfacing now with AI agents and requiring durable executions specifically for that?
So I think this is a really new and emerging use case for deboss.
So actually besides AI agents, we also have another AI use case which is AI data pipeline.
If we have time we can dive into that as well.
And for AI agents basically the program will be driven by AI or LLMs.
So say instead of developers coding what functions to call the function calling.
or tool calling will be decided based on the LLM responses.
So I actually I built a very interesting refund agent uh using langraph and deboss.
So basically what an agent does is that when they receive a refund request,
it will talk to LM to decide which tool to use.
Maybe based on the customer record, based on the order, it will call a refund workflow.
So very simplistically, am I right in.
that the agent is essentially an LLM with tools at the most basic level?
Yeah. Okay. Sorry, continue.
Yeah.
So then like the agent can say basically oh.
if the purchase was above a threshold I will need to send an email to an admin to. verify whether you.
want to approve this refund.
or not and then the refund workflow will have to wait for human input.
and then decide what to do next.
So I would say with AI agent the most challenging part is first dynamic execution of workflows.
you can no longer have a very static workflow like workflow branches.
or function calling will be very dynamic based on the LLM output.
and second it's really unreliable in many ways like from my point of view we treat AI as.
a unreliable service in the stack so your AI call may fail.
and then every time you call it it may give you a different result.
and then third thing is that human in the loop is really tricky like how do we make.
AI I work together with human is a kind of new. and challenging topic these days.
Can you talk talk more about the agent you developed and how you use deboss there?
Yeah.
So for the agent I developed basically I decorate my tool function as a deboss workflow.
So that it will guarantee basically if I refunded it before I will only refund it once.
So this guarantees that if the user ask I want to refund it again based on the recorded.
information we'll say you've already been refunded before so we'll skip. the refund.
and they will guarantee that once we kick off the refund workflow it will always finish.
So say if something happened to the program.
if it crashes in the middle we will just resume the refund process from where it left off.
So like say if I already process the payment.
or kind of return the money back to user will also restore the inventory and stuff like that.
Basic question though.
So if the agent is the LLM with tool.
and the LLM is the one calling the tool.
which in many cases the tool is an API call.
How does now deboss get involved in that part of the workflow?
Yeah, exactly.
So the cool thing is that as I introduced before deboss is a library.
and annotations that you can wrap around your function with.
So when lm calls the function it will call the wrapped function.
and that wrap function is a dual workflow.
So that's why it's super easy to add deboss with any AI frameworks.
Like instead of passing your bare function, you pass the annotated function into your AI tools.
That's interesting.
Are you going to talk about data pipelines as well? Is there an example there?
Yeah.
So data pipeline is one like huge use case in deboss.
where basically the typical pipeline sometimes goes the first is a workflow will first scrape websites.
or scrape other data sources and store the PDFs or images into some S3 bucket.
and then the second step will in parallel we'll use LMS to analyze those images or PDFs.
and then the third step will be to persist the return value from LLMs into multiple data stores.
either vector database or Postgress or you know multiple data sources. Yeah.
And then maybe another step is to do some decision based on.
or analytics based on the results from previous steps like a concrete use case is for example stock. marketing monitoring.
So some of our use cases would be to scrape the website of stock stock markets.
and then put into LM to some do some analysis.
and then do some business decision based on like do I want to invest in the stock?
Do I want to sell the stocks as a final step?
Why durable execution?
Yeah, durable execution is essential because you don't want to lose data.
and once you proc like usually there are two reasons.
One, the data volume is huge, right?
So easily you can process 1,000 documents and if something fell in the middle.
or not just 1,000 maybe 10,000 documents.
if something fell in the middle you don't want to restart from the beginning like you don't want.
to say oh now something.
happened to my pipeline either the AI failed.
or I I hit some AI rate limit.
I don't want to say I have to reprocess all 10,000 documents again.
I want to resume from where it left off.
So that's the first thing.
The second thing is you want everything to complete.
Say if I process 10,000 documents, I want all of them to complete.
Otherwise, my business decision for example, which stock to trade may be based on incomplete data.
that can cause like financial loss and other sequence consequences.
So in this specific example, if I did decorate the loading step with deboss.
and the error was on let's say the 100,000 document in my set of 500,000 what is the. behavior?
So basically in this case you want to use deboss cues to paralyze those tasks like you don't.
want to process those all those documents in one giant step.
You want to make sure that you want to.
basically say each step is a cued task spawned by my workflow like from documents 1 to 10,000.
I will incue. a task.
and then it will become a fan out pattern and then we will wait until all tasks finish.
So I will fan in by waiting those results.
So if any of the tasks failed.
then we'll when we recover the workflow we'll just say.
okay now I have to check all those cute tasks.
and if some tasks failed then we'll restart execution of those tasks.
but for those tasks that have already finished we'll just get the result from the database. and then return it.
So that's how you can correctly recover from those failures.
So you had earlier mentioned about using conductor for deboss in production.
Besides that, are there other recommendations about being able to run deboss at scale?
Yeah.
So the question is mostly about like the best practices for using deboss.
Mhm. Yeah.
So I think to run deboss at scale,
you first really want to make sure that your workflows are deterministic.
That's the core to guarantee your workflows are recoverable.
because if you're you have nondeterminism in your workflow.
when we recover it we may go through another execution path.
that will we don't really know how to recover.
And then the second thing is use cues wisely.
So for example when you deal with LLMs they typically have rate limiting.
and they also have concurrency limits.
So how many outstanding requests you can have to those LLMs.
So in this case use deboss cues.
So with cues you can add ray limiter.
Say I want at most five API calls uh within like 30 seconds.
and I want at most 10 outstanding requests at a time.
So with those primitives you can build your apps with parallel task.
but also within the limit of those LLMs.
Is there anything else you'd like to add for folks.
that would like to get started with deboss transact?
Yeah.
So for deboss transact, download it, install it, run it locally on your laptop.
The cool thing is that because it's a library, we can also leverage the debugger.
So we actually develop a time travel debugger.
that you can install from VS Code marketplace.
where you will be able to replay traces happened in anything happened. in the past.
say I want to investigate why the workflow executed.
that way like executed yesterday then I will just pick the workflow.
and then tell our debugger extension to say I want to re-execute that.
and when we reexecute instead of writing to the database we'll just pull the information from the database.
say this is the workflow this was the input.
and those were the output of each step so we can instead of actually.
so say if your workflow contains sending email.
or calling out to stripe we will not actually call those external APIs will.
instead return the recorded information.
and then you'll be able to step through your workflow as if it happened in the past. So that's very cool.
Thanks so much for today Chan.
I think a lot of the goal of the conversation.
at least what I was trying to achieve was distinguish between workflow as a graphical representation aid for.
business users versus grouping together the series of steps.
or services that need to be durable.
and how does that play into the now.
where a lot of the code generation is happening with AI as um where exactly.
does deboss fit into it?
You've explained that you can definitely use the simplicity of deboss.
and the performance of deboss in grouping together steps that you need as a workflow.
and I presume one would be able to use AI to.
then introspect that code and generate the graphical representation as required for business users.
But then the question would be why would you not use AI to even write all the framework.
that comes with deboss.
Could you just maybe spend a few minutes on your thinking about how AI fits into all this? Yeah.
So it's a really interesting question and I've been thinking a lot about it recently especially with AI.
We've seen a lot of AI generated code.
It's true that someone may say okay AI may be able to generate those checkpointing code.
but AI won't be able to generate automatic workflow recovery it won't be able to generate the control.
plane that can automatically recover on failure.
so we think deboss and other workflow engines still played an essential role here in the AI era. right.
and then with AI generated code I think we really want to make sure they are reliable.
and by reliable I mean like yes those codes may be buggy.
so You want to have a way to say if I caught a bug,
I want to be able to investigate a bug.
I want to be able to say restart my workflow from a specific step. and then fix the bug.
So those are the capabilities where those durable execution engines really shine.
because with those AI generated unreliable code like you want a way to correctly store those information for.
debugging.
and because I think the one advantage of deboss is.
that because we store those like what step has executed.
and at when the time stamp of it in a relational database.
So we we really have this structured data for AI to analyze.
It's easy for human to analyze and it will.
also be easy for AI to analyze what's going wrong.
So I think it's a really exciting new capability.
that we are exploring and I think simplicity and structured data logging are important.
So simplicity is that we actually try to add a prompt for deboss.
and we give the prompt that will incorporate our latest version of the code.
We'll basically give AI instructions on how to add deboss to your code.
So with that we can just tell AI make this code durable.
and then AI will correctly do that in one shot.
And that's really interesting because if we put dual execution as a library,
we will be able to make AI generated code durable very easily.
And then when you execute that code, we automatically checkpoint data in a database.
So it will be very easy for a human or for AI to investigate what's going on.
And then because everything is a database, it also allows users or AI to automatically fix those code.
because to fix those code you just need several SQL statements to modify the table to change the.
result to change the output of the recorded outputs table.
and then to continue from where you left off.
So like we are really exploring the synergy between your code your database.
and the way to modify your code to generate new traces to modify the database to observe databases.
So like it's a really exciting area.
How can listeners contact you if they have any feedback or questions?
Yeah, so to contact me can visit my website chanley.dev.
You can follow me on LinkedIn, follow me on Blue Sky or Twitter,
but also don't forget to visit deboss.dev.
This is our main website and we're looking forward to your feedback.
Thank you so much Han for coming on.
Thanks Kran for inviting me.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by E Software Magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio is licensed under Creative Common License 2.5. Thanks for listening.